<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>io.github.trendorin.Verbuno</id>
  <name>Verbuno</name>
  <summary>Native Linux translation through your own AI provider</summary>
  <developer id="io.github.trendorin">
    <name>Trendorin</name>
  </developer>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0-or-later</project_license>
  <description>
    <p>Verbuno is a lightweight C++ and Qt 6 Widgets translation client that stays available from the Linux system tray.</p>
    <p>It connects directly to OpenRouter or another OpenAI-compatible endpoint selected by the user. It has no telemetry and stores API keys only in the desktop keychain.</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Translate between a broad catalog of languages with streamed output.</li>
      <li>Extract editable text from opened, pasted or dropped photos using local Tesseract OCR.</li>
      <li>Choose any model or refresh the current OpenRouter free-model catalog.</li>
      <li>Restrict OpenRouter routing by data-collection and Zero Data Retention policies.</li>
      <li>Keep local history only when explicitly enabled.</li>
    </ul>
  </description>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">io.github.trendorin.Verbuno.desktop</launchable>
  <provides>
    <binary>verbuno</binary>
  </provides>
  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/Trendorin/Verbuno</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/Trendorin/Verbuno/issues</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/Trendorin/Verbuno</url>
  <content_rating type="oars-1.1"/>
  <releases>
    <release version="0.3.1" date="2026-07-20">
      <description>
        <p>Made local preferences verifiably persistent, enabled secure remembered API keys by default, and added visible storage and credential status.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.0" date="2026-07-20">
      <description>
        <p>Added asynchronous local photo OCR with image preview, installed-language discovery, layout modes, confidence feedback and an explicit review-before-translation workflow.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.2.0" date="2026-07-19">
      <description>
        <p>Renamed the application to Verbuno, removed the optional context field, and added the actual routed OpenRouter provider and model to the interface and local history.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.1" date="2026-07-19">
      <description>
        <p>Added a standard system-decorated window, visible provider and model information, and runtime English, Russian, Ukrainian and German interfaces.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.0" date="2026-07-19">
      <description>
        <p>Initial native Linux release with tray popup, OpenRouter streaming, secure key storage, privacy routing, optional local history, and native packages.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
